International Council of Women Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
International Council of Women Records 1931-1957
MSS27235
International Council of Women
4,200 items
6 containers
2.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
International federation of national women’s organizations; affiliated with the United Nations. Correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, press releases, and publications concerning the involvement of the International Council of Women in educational cinematography, peace and disarmament, and other global issues.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
Organizations
Conference of International Non-governmental Organizations.; Disarmament Committee of the Women's International Organisations.; International Council of Women.; International Educational Cinematographic Institute.; League of Nations.; Peace and Disarmament Committee of the Women's International Organisations.; United Nations.
Subjects
Cinematography.; Disarmament.; Education.; Motion pictures in education--Congresses.; Peace.; Women--International cooperation.; Women--Societies, etc.
Provenance
The records of the International Council of Women were given to the Library of Congress by the council in 1957 and by C. Dreyfus-Barney in 1959.
Other Repositories
Most of the records of the International Council of Women secretariat are held by the Centre d’Archives pour l’Histoire des Femmes in Brussels, Belgium. Earlier records of the ICW are in the William Allan Neilson Library of Smith College in Northampton, Massachusetts. The records of the National Council of Women, the American affiliate of the ICW, are held by the New York Public Library, New York, New York, and are available on microform.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the International Council of Women are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the International Council of Women (ICW) span the years 1931-1957. The ICW, founded in Washington, D.C., in 1888 and now headquartered in Paris, is comprised of various women’s organizations.
The records of the International Council of Women in the Library of Congress focus on its activities in three areas during the years prior to World War II. They include correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, and publications concerning the ICW’s involvement in two pioneer conferences on educational films held at the International Institute of Educational Cinematography of the League of Nations, in 1931 and 1934. Also included is material relating to the Conference of International Non-Governmental Organizations, 1948-1954, and its involvement in the work of the Peace and Disarmament Committee of the Women’s International Organisations.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
Container List
- Bulletin, International Council of Women, 1940-1944, (4 folders) (Box 1)
- Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments (circa 1934), 1931-1935, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Conference of International Non-Governmental Organizations (Box 1)
  - General conferences (Box 1)
    - 1949-1950, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1950-1957, undated (Box 2)
  - Regional conferences, 1957 (Box 2)
- Conference on Cinematography and Broadcasting (1931), 1931 (Box 2)
- Educational cinematography, 1936, 1956 (Box 2)
- Institute of Public Affairs (Box 2)
  - 1941-1942, (4 folders) (Box 2)
- International Congress on Teaching and Educational Films (1934), 1934 (Box 3)
- Peace and Disarmament Committee, Women’s International Organisations, 1931-1937 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Dreyfus-Barney, Laura (Box 3)
      - Dingmam, Mary, 1931-1937, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      - General (Box 3)
        - 1931-1932, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - 1934-1937, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - General, 1932-1936 (Box 4)
  - Minutes of meetings (Box 4)
    - 1931-1933, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1934-1937, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Miscellany (Box 5)
    - 1932-1934, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1935-1937, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Press releases, 1931-1937, (3 folders) (Box 6)
- Woman’s Centennial Congress (1940), 1940 (Box 6)